Hello and welcome to the lecture where we explore
microprocessors by learning machine language and
assembly language and re-implementing software
in the lowest possible language. So we're going
to start with our two instruction CPU from the
previous section and look kind of what it did
and what it didn't do. Uh because our next CPU is
going to have more data, we're going to have to
learn hexadecimal notation instead of base 2. And
then we're going to take a look at the foundations
of programming from Python for everybody. Uh
sequential, conditional, and iteration-based
programming. And we're going to re-implement all
those things in machine language and and assembly
language. We'll take a look at real CPUs that are
in the in the market now like Intel x86 and ARM.
And then the historical CPU, the the 6502. Um,
the CPU that we're going to simulate and build
is called the CD I called it the CDC 6504. It
really is mostly a 6502. Um, with some homage to
the first machine language that I ever knew, which
was the CDC 6500. So, we're going to learn about
the architecture registers, those kinds of things.
And then machine language, the actual zeros and
ones that the 6502 executes. And then assembly
language, it's is a very low-level uh language
which has a one-to-one correspondence with machine
language. And after we've played with an emulator
long enough, we'll realize that, you know,
emulators can be a pretty cool thing. And they're
actually not that hard to not that hard to write.
And we'll look at some of the emulators like
WASM and JavaScript. We're going to take a look
at how Internet Archive uh keeps old games alive
using a series of emulators that run all inside
your browser. And then we're going to finish up
talking about CPU evolution over the decades. So
if we take a look at the end of the lecture in
the previous section, we had built a CPU that had
in effect one 4-bit register, one 4-bit adder, a
clock, and then one instruction that chose between
whether or not we reset the register, the latch,
or we incremented the latch. And interestingly,
that's where we're going to start. But like what
is missing? And and the answer is if we go all
the way back to chapter 1, slide 19, Python for
everybody, a class that I started teaching in
the mid 2000s. Basically, what we're missing is
instructions that are coming from the main memory
to program the central processing unit. And those
instructions guide the central processing unit
as to how to use the hardware inside that central
processing unit. And those instructions
are zeros and ones that are represented
by electrical impulses that are coming into the
central processor. If we look at a little more
detail in the central processor, there's a number
of different resources in the central processor.
There is the ALU the arithmetic and logic unit
which has adders comparison multipliers sometimes
and then there is a place we store super fast
data to feed to and from the ALU the registers
so usually the ALU doesn't operate on things that
are in the memory we load data into the registers
and then we do computations with the ALU the PC
or program counter is the most important register
of all because it tells tells the CPU where in the
memory to retrieve the next instruction. So based
on where the PC is pointing, the CPU retrieves a
me an instruction from the memory and the register
CIR current instruction register which is not
shown on a lot of architecture diagrams but in
a sense the the machine code the 8, 16 or more
bits is loaded into the CPU in a register and
then it does what's called decoding and that is
it looks at the bits says if this an add is this
a subtract is this an increment is this a clear
what is the instruction uction and then what the
decoder does is it in effect sends signals to
the rest of the parts of the central processing
unit to take say oh okay we're going to add so
take this register feed it to the ALU add this
other register and then take the result from that
addition and put it into a different register and
of course there's a clock and the clock causes the
logic to happen our emulator is going to run on
a one hertz clock which is one one instruction
per second and um the real 6502 is 1 megahertz
which is a million instructions per second which
of course compared to modern processors is not
very many. So the machine language instructions
that we're going to do are going to be 8 bits and
there is an assembly language which is a symbolic
representation like if we want to clear the X
register set it to zero then we have an op code of
1 1 0 0 1 0 and so you can just see these op codes
for various things. There's a clear we're showing
an increment a load constant a load from memory
and then a store back to memory. We're going to
see lots of these. So, so don't don't slow down
uh and learn this. Um and so up next, we're
going to learn hexadecimal because the more
data we have, the we can't just use base 2 for
everything because it's not a very dense format.
[Music] [Applause] [Music]